Today, it's our pleasure to host
Nouamane Tazi from Hugging Face.
He's the lead author of
the Ultra-Scale Playbook
and a core developer
of Nanotronics,
Hugging Face's open source
distributed training library.
His work expands projects
like Star StarCoder 2,
Small LLM 3, and mixture
of expert scaling
with several initiatives.
And he is passionate about
making large scale training
practical and accessible.
So without further ado,
let me hand it off to him.
Thank you so much
for the invitation.
So hello, everyone.
My name is Nouamane Tazi.
I've been working with Hugging
Face now for four years.
And the talk for today
is Scaling Training
to Thousands of GPUs.
So today's talk is going to
be mainly inspired by the book
that Hugging Face made.
It's called
Ultra-Scale Playbook.
So make sure to check it out.
It's available online and
there is a printed version
if you need it.
But I also added some
elements since the book now
dates from one year
ago, especially
regarding MOE scaling
and some new things
that we can take a look at.
So without further ado, let's
start with the first question
is, why does scaling matter?
And if we take a look at the
latest releases of the latest
LLMs, we can see that
the trend is still
to train larger and larger.
And why is that?
That's also because
we can see that there
is a correlation
with intelligence.
It seems that the bigger the
LLMs are, the smarter they are.
And there's just an example
from this week, Kimi K2.6,
which is also one
trillion parameter model.
So to take just some
numbers, models of these days
are one trillion parameter
large, or even larger.
They get trained on 15
trillion training tokens
and for context lengths
as far as one million.
So how can we do that?
Now, to take some quick
overview about what
does this entail from
a infra point of view.
So if you want to train
this kind of model,
first, you need to
load the data, which
is about 15 trillion.
Imagine that's stored
on a storage somewhere,
and you need to load
that continuously
in your training loop.
And each training
iteration, even if the model
is as big as one
trillion parameter model,
needs to take about one second.
And you're limited by the
memory within each GPU or TPU
or whatever you're using.
And you need to save
checkpoints to that storage
every now and then.
So you're putting a lot of
pressure into these GPUs.
So the talk of today is
going to be mainly focused
on training, the training
iteration or the training.
So let's start
quickly on one GPU.
So there is a model.
We do forward, backward.
We compute gradients, and
then we do the optimizer step
and we have an updated model.
But for our case, we usually
have global batch size
of one million to 10 million,
even like 50 million tokens.
So that, of course, doesn't fit
on a single training iteration.
So what we do usually is we
can do gradient accumulation.
So we're going to divide the
batch size to smaller batch
sizes.
And we're going to do multiple
forward and backwards.
And we're going to accumulate
gradients sequentially.
The problem with
this approach is
we're going to assume that the
model already fits in memory,
which is not always the case.
Models now are so
big, one trillion.
And we said that
we're still limited
by the available VRAM in each
accelerator you're going to use.
So how can we solve
this with more GPUs?
The other thing is that
if you train sequentially
with this approach, you're going
to need to wait for a long time.
So if we have more GPUs,
how can we speed this up?
And for this, there is multiple
forms of parallelism we can use.
And each one of them is
used in a specific use case.
And hopefully today, you can
get at least an intuition
which parallelism you can
use for which use case.
And to help you--
so basically for
today, I'm going
to mainly focus on the
first two parallelisms
because they're going to explain
just the intuition of how we can
think about these parallelism.
And the final three, we're going
to just quickly skim over them
because there's not enough time.
And I think that the
approach can be generalized.
So before starting, a few notes.
So this approach can be applied
to an accelerator, GPUs, TPUs.
So in the slides, I
use GPUs, but the same
can be applied for anything.
And it's useful for
pre-training, post-training,
distillation
training, inference.
So any type of workload can
benefit from these parallelisms.
And it's applicable.
You don't need 1,000 GPUs
to benefit from this.
As long as you
have two, at least,
you can benefit from
these parallelism.
So naively, what we want to do?
So we said that the
model doesn't fit.
So ideally, we want to be
able to shard the model,
so either vertically
or horizontally.
And that means we're
going to also shard
the gradients and the
optimizer and shard the data.
Because we don't
want to wait too long
to train sequentially on data.
So let's deep dive into scaling.
And first of all, we're going
to start with data parallelism.
And I'm assuming this
is the basic form
that everyone is using.
So I'm going to go
quickly over it.
So instead of
training sequentially
over multiple batches, I'm going
to feed each batch to a GPU.
So I'm going to have
different batches per GPU.
Thus, the name data parallelism.
I'm going to shard the data.
And of course, if I have
different data per GPU,
each GPU is going to
compute different gradients.
And to keep the same model
duplicated on each GPU,
I'm going to need to
synchronize these gradients.
And how am I going to do that?
It's going to be the same
as accumulating gradient,
but it's going to be in
a distributed fashion.
Thus, we're going to need to
use the AllReduce collective
operation, which is
just a distributed
sum over multiple GPUs.
So we end up with
the same gradients,
and thus, we can do the same
optimizer step over all GPUs.
And if you want to take
a look at the code,
it's going to look like this.
We can use the DDP
class by PyTorch.
And when you wrap
your model with it,
when you do the
forward and backward,
it automatically handles the
AllReduce part in the backward.
So there is a small
problem with this.
When we do the AllReduce, the
GPU stay idle in that time.
And for that, there is a very
nice tool called torch.profiler
that helps you visualize what
the timeline is basically,
or the workflow for
the CPU and GPU.
And for example, if we apply
it on a naive implementation
of DDP, we can see that there
is a CPU stream that is forward
and backward.
And then there is the GPU
streams, GPU computation
and communication.
So there is two things.
So the biggest
thing that we want
is we don't want
GPU to stay idle.
So we definitely want the
GPU computation stream
to be always full, which
is not the case in here,
as we can see here.
The other thing is
we need to make sure
that the CPU is always
ahead of the GPU,
so that we can always
schedule kernels beforehand.
And the third thing is, for
example, in this case of DDP,
we can see that the
AllReduce is not overlapped
with the computation.
So ideally, we want to
overlap this communication
with computation.
So this is a simplified
diagram of the previous.
So how can we overlap
this AllReduce?
We can just start
AllReduce in the gradient
once a bucket of the
gradients is computed.
Basically when you
do the forward,
you start doing the backward
from the last layers.
So you don't need to do the
backward of the entire model
to be able to AllReduce them.
So once, for
example, you compute
the gradient of
the last layer, you
can already start the AllReduce.
And this is what
we do in practice.
So for example, if
2 is the last layer,
once the gradients of the
last layer is computed,
we can AllReduce it and we can
continue doing the backward.
And this bucket can-- we
control the size of this bucket
in PyTorch via this argument
bucket cup micro-batch--
microbits.
So you can control how big or
how small the bucket should
be, so that you have a better
overlap of communication
and computation.
And this is what goes through
the mind of any engineer who
tries to scale models.
Basically, when you
have a lot of GPUs,
you definitely want to overlap
efficiently your computation
with communication so that
you avoid any idle time here
for the GPU computation
and to benefit
of the tensor cores of GPUs.
So this is the end goal
of this presentation.
So quickly, you can
go over a recap of DP.
So it's easy to implement.
It's very efficiently
overlapped.
It's really good.
And it's model agnostic, right?
So we can just wrap
any model and it's
going to automatically reduce
the gradients in the backward.
But the problem is
that the optimizer step
is duplicated across GPUs.
Because if you have the same
model in each of your GPU,
all of them are going
to do the same optimizer
step, which is bad.
It's duplicated work.
The second thing is that
if you scale more and more
in the number of
GPUs, you're also
going to need more and
more batches of data.
And this is what we
call global batch size.
So your global batch size
is also going to scale.
But of course, you can't
just scale indefinitely.
We're limited by tens
of millions of tokens.
And so you can just
apply DP-- if you have,
I don't know, one
million GPUs, you
can just use the DP
over all of your GPUs.
And the third thing, which
is the biggest bottleneck,
is that DP assumes that the
training step fits in memory.
And this is not always
the case, unfortunately.
And so we need other
approaches to optimize memory.
And we can look at the
first one, which is DP ZeRO.
So from the name,
DP ZeRO 1 tries
to solve the optimizer step.
Basically, we said
that in DP we're
going to duplicate the
model and all of them
are going to do the
same optimizer step.
So how can we reduce the memory
at least of the optimizer states
so that they're not
duplicated and each GPU can
do a different part of the
optimizer-- of the optimization?
So the simplest approach is
instead of having the optimizer
states of all the
models, I'm going
to shard them across my GPUs.
And when I do the
backward step, I'm
only going to reduce
scatter the gradients.
So I'm not going to have
all the reduce here.
I'm only going to
have reduce scatter.
And then I'm going to do the
optimizer step for each shard.
And this is what's
really good about ZeRO 1.
We're not going to
have duplicated work.
And once I have my
updated parameter shards,
I need to all gather them
before the next step.
So this is ZeRO 1 in brief.
And there is s very
important intuition
that you can learn from this.
So before in Vanilla DP, we had
an AllReduce in the backward,
right?
In here, we had an AllReduce.
And the trick that we
made for ZeRO 1 to work
is that we replaced the
AllReduce with a reduce scatter
and an all gather.
And this works great.
And we're going to reuse
this trick in the future.
Why?
Because AllReduce, essentially,
is just a reduce-scatter
plus an all-gather.
So basically, we didn't
add any communication.
It's the same communication.
It's just that instead
of doing the AllReduce,
I did reduce-scatter
first so that-- to compute
the gradients first.
And then I can do
the optimizer step.
And then I all-gather
the parameters.
The second thing is
for the gradients,
I didn't use all of them, right?
So when I did the
reduce scatter,
I only used the shards
that I optimized later.
So I can just throw
the parts that I
don't need from the gradients.
And this is ZeRO 2.
So ZeRO 2 optimizes or
saves memory even further
by just discarding the
gradients that I don't use.
And this is the difference
between ZeRO 1 and ZeRO 2.
It's a small difference.
It's just that I don't
need to keep the gradients.
So it's easier said than done.
Because in the
implementation, it's
annoying to just discard things.
So people usually just use ZeRO
1 and they keep the gradients.
And also an important note since
now there is Muon optimizer,
optimizer requires the
full tensors grads.
So previously, people would
take their entire parameters,
and they would just shard them.
They would flatten everything.
So we don't keep the
notion of a tensor.
You just flatten
all your parameters,
and then you would shard
them along the number of GPUs
you have.
But the problem is for Muon, you
can just split your parameters.
You want your tensors to be full
so that you can do the Newton
optimization on them.
So the thing is
here, when you want
to split your parameters or
your gradients on your GPUs,
you need to make sure to
keep your tensors full.
So for example, I'm going to
give the first, I don't know,
five full tensors to the
first GPU and the five--
the second five tensors
to the second GPU.
So this is for Muon, but
also for other optimizers.
And lastly, for
ZeRO 3, I also want
to save memory of
the parameters.
And this is the craziest part,
because how can I save memory
by sharding the
model's memory when
I need them in the
forward and the backward?
And there is a very nice trick
that the ZeRO 3 engineers came
from-- came with is when
I do the optimizer step,
I don't need to all
gather right away.
I can just keep the shards
of the model on each GPU,
and whenever I need to do
the forward of that layer,
for example, for
the first layer,
I'm just going to ask
for these other shards
from the other GPUs.
So for example, for
the first layer,
I'm going to ask for
the other shards.
I'm going to do the forward.
And then I'm going to
free the other parameters.
And then for the other layer,
I'm going to do the same thing.
So this looks very slow, right?
Because on each layer, you
need to ask for all the--
for the rest of your parameters
from your other GPUs,
do the forward and
then free them.
But in practice,
it works very well.
And the reason is--
by the way, it's the
same for the backward.
So for the backward,
we also just do
the all-gather of the weights
and then compute the backward
and we free the weights.
So the reason is we
prefetch the next layer
while computing
the current layer.
So this is the trick.
So I had previously
an all-gather
here after the optimizer step.
But now, I just separated the
all-gather on multiple layers.
And for example,
for the first layer,
I'm going to all-gather it here.
I'm going to do the compute.
And while I'm computing for
the forward of the first layer,
I'm already all-gathering
the next layer, et cetera.
And then I free it, et cetera.
And so concretely, I
never have more than two
what we call FSDP modules
or FSDP units in my memory,
because I always free one when
I all-gather the other one.
And the same thing
for the backward.
And so I still do the
distributed optimizer and I
repeat.
So this is basically the best
form of DP that we can have.
Why?
Because I efficiently
optimize my memory.
I saved memory on
optimizer states,
on gradients, and on the model.
And I also prefetch.
So everything is
very well-overlapped.
And besides that, similar
to DP's bucket size,
I can also control the
size of the buckets, which
we call the size of the
FSDP modules that we have.
And so for the code-- so
there is two-- by the way,
ZeRO 3 is also called FSDP.
FSDP is fully sharded
data parallel.
And there is two
versions in PyTorch.
So FSDP1, we used to
just have a class FSDP
where we can wrap
our model and we
can define the
wrap policy, which
is similar to the bucket size.
And for FSDP2, there is now a
function called fully shard.
And you just call
it over your model
and it's going to
automatically transform
your modules to FSDP modules.
So the difference between the
two versions, the first one,
as I said, it flattens
all of your parameters
and we already talked
of the problems of that.
For example, Muon
and some optimizers,
they need full tensors,
and this is bad.
So ideally, when you
shard your parameters,
you want to keep full
tensors on each GPU.
So FSDP2 enables that.
The second thing is
FSDP2 uses DTensor, which
is a new utility in PyTorch.
And it helps being combined
with other forms of parallelism
as we're going to see.
And so to recap, please
compare ZeRO 2 with ZeRO 3.
So in ZeRO 2, we had
a big all-gather here
to all-gather the parameters
that we optimized.
And in ZeRO 3, I just
divided this big all-gather
into smaller all gathers of
the different FSDP modules.
So it allows me to overlap this
all gather with the forwards.
And I can control the
size of the FSDP modules.
And it's also model
agnostic, because I
don't care about the
architecture of my model.
And it's just great.
It works very good.
So the pros and
cons of DP ZeRO 3.
It creates memory for comms.
So DP Vanilla, I didn't
optimize memory at all.
I just assumed that the
model fits in memory.
But if I needed to save memory,
I can just do ZeRO 1 or ZeRO 3
or ZeRO 2 or ZeRO 3.
And this is something
to pay attention to.
So a lot of people just throw
FSDP2 on all of their models.
And this is not a good thing.
Because if your model
fits on GPUs with ZeRO 1,
you don't need ZeRO
3 because ZeRO 3
you're going to add more
communications than you're going
to make your training slower.
So just use the ZeRO degree
that you need to save
memory, because there
is no other benefits.
If ZeRO 1 fits, it's going
to be faster than ZeRO 3.
So the second thing is the great
overlap of comms with compute.
As we've seen, everything
is well-overlapped.
And the third thing
is model-agnostic.
So there is no headache
of implementation.
You can just-- whatever
the PyTorch module is,
you can just wrap it with FSDP.
You don't care if
it's a state model.
You don't care if it's anything.
It's going to work
out of the box.
The negatives, though,
is that at scale,
since you need to all-gather the
parameters for each FSDP module,
if you scale it too much,
even if it's overlapped,
you can't hide the
communication anymore,
because it's not perfect.
If you have a very slow network,
you cannot overlap that anymore.
So there is a solution
for that, which is
called hybrid sharding or HSDP.
So you would use FSDP on a
slow-- on a smaller circle.
And on the larger circle,
you can use Vanilla DP.
So this is something
you can look up later.
And the other thing
is ZeRO 3 is--
we're still in data parallel.
So we're still
scaling with batches.
So every GPU has
a different batch.
And we still have
this restriction.
We can't scale indefinitely.
So what if I reached
my global batch size?
So I have, I don't
know, 10,000 GPUs.
And at 1,000 GPUs, I already
reach my global batch size.
I need another form
of parallelism.
So let's take a look at TP.
And the motivation
behind tensor parallelism
is that if I have a model,
transformer model, for example,
I want to keep the same
batch, so the same inputs,
the same data, and
chart the model so
that I do the same computation
as if I had one GPU.
So basically, instead of doing
the computation with one GPU.
I would do it with two.
And essentially,
I'm going to shard
the memory for my model for
my gradients optimizer states
by the number of GPUs I have.
So the question is-- and
this is a very fun question
that people like to ask
in interviews, et cetera.
So do we cope-- do we keep
full or half activations
in tensor parallel?
And we're going to
answer that after a bit.
So let's start with
an easy example, which
is matrix multiplication.
So if we take X
multiplied by Y--
by W here, a simple
approach, and we want
to parallelize that onto GPUs.
We can just split our
Matrix on columns.
And then I can
all-gather the outputs.
Let's take the example
of two matmuls now.
So I have Y1, which is X
multiplied YW1, and Y2, which
is Y2 multiplied by W2.
So if I split my first
weight by columns
and if I split the
second one by rows,
I can do the same computation,
which is two multiplications.
And then I do an
AllReduce here, and I
would get the same result
and the same computation
as if I did this with one GPU.
So this is the power
of tensor parallelism,
and this is the
intuition behind it.
If I had one GPU, I would
do two matrix multiplication
with the full matrices.
So I managed to distribute
this operation on two GPUs
by splitting the weights.
So each GPU only
has half the weights
and each GPU only
does half the compute.
But the caveat of
this is that I need
to do a distributed
communication on AllReduce
to keep the correctness.
How does this work for
the backward, though?
It's the same thing.
And again, I'm going
to assume that I
have the same upstream grad,
and this is a big headache.
We can talk about it in a bit.
So if we assume that I have
the same upstream grad, which
is this, the Y2 and
Y2, similarly, it's
just going to be multiplied
by the transpose of W2 and W1.
This is, of course, to
compute the dx, which
is the Dout, the out gradient.
So again, it's just--
I'm going to do
two multiplication.
And again, it's just
half the weights.
And again, I just need
to do an AllReduce.
So to efficiently distribute
two matrix multiplications
on multiple GPUs,
I'm going to need
one AllReduce in the
forward and one AllReduce
in the backward
under the assumption
that I have the same upstream
gradients, which is the outputs,
and I had the same inputs.
So let's apply this on our MLP.
So in MLP, we have, for example,
Y activation of X times A.
And then I multiply
it by another matrix.
So I always going to have
two matrix multiplications.
So I apply the same trick.
The first one is going
to be a column linear.
The second one is a row linear.
And I need an AllReduce
to keep the math correct.
And as we said, we assume--
and this is a big assumption.
In our transformer,
we assume that I'm
going to always have the same
activations, the same inputs,
the same data, and I need to
have the same output and later
the same upstream gradients.
So all the operations
after that must
be the same in the two GPUs.
And another thing to
basically what we said,
we're going to divide
the compute by half.
So A1 and A2 are halves of
the original matrix A, right?
So hidden_dim is
sharded in here.
And this is what we just said.
We need the same input.
And we need the same
upstream gradient
to keep the math correct.
Let's take an
example of attention.
So for attention, similarly, we
have two matrix multiplication,
which is the QKV projections
and the output projections.
So the question would
be should we shard along
a hidden dimension or
number of heads or both.
And what does it mean?
So the question you
really want to ask--
and this is a very
generic question.
If you have a
model and you don't
know how to implement
tensor parallelism on it,
or you want to check that the
implementation is correct,
you should really
ask, would GPUs
compute the same
activations as without TP?
So let's say I sharded
a long head dimension.
Then when I do the softmax,
which is Q times K,
it's going to have a
reduced hidden dimension.
And that would impact
the softmax calculation.
So it wouldn't give the same
results as if I had a TP one.
But if I sharded a
long number of heads,
since the heads
are independent, I
would get the same activations
as if I didn't use TP.
So this is really
the whole thing.
So we showed a long
number of heads
since the attention heads are
independent to keep attention
correct.
And again, we need
the same inputs,
and we need the same
upstream gradients.
So as a recap, the pros
is that we shard the model
and compute across
GPUs and we're
memory and sample efficient.
So at the same time,
I sharded memory.
So model parameters gradients
and optimizer states.
And I didn't need to
have multiple batches.
So I used the same
sample across my GPUs.
The second thing I didn't need
an AllReduce for the gradients
because all GPUs I'm assuming
they're doing the same work.
It's like I have
one big GPU that I
distributed on smaller GPUs.
And the cons is that
communication is heavy
because at each attention,
at each MLP block,
I need to do an
AllReduce for the forward
and for the backward.
The second thing is-- and this
is something we can see later.
The parameters that are
outside the TP region,
which is the region where the
hidden dimension is sharded,
should stay synchronized.
Otherwise, I won't
have the same inputs
and the same upstream
gradients because this
is a big assumption for the
matmuls to stay correct.
So in practice, the parameters
that are outside the TP region,
they need to stay the same.
They need to stay duplicated.
So in practice, we all
reduce their grads.
And this is something
that screws up training
when you use TP.
And just due to
numerical precision--
because theoretically,
you don't need to do this,
but due to numerical
imprecisions, they drift apart.
So in practice, we
always use their grads.
And the third thing is, of
course, complex implementation.
And it's not easy if you
change the architecture.
Let's say you want to use MLA
or some other fancy attention.
It's a headache to apply
tensor parallelism on it.
So let's take a look at
sequence parallelism.
So what's the motivation
behind sequence parallelism,
which is a flavor to TP?
So in TP, we've
seen that we have
this TP region, which
is the attention,
and this TP region,
which is the MLP.
And we do the AllReduce here.
So the second layers,
which are the row layers,
they have an AllReduce.
OK, cool.
So in the TP region, the
shape is a sequence patch
and we shard the hidden
dimension we set.
And after the second
matrix in each TP region,
I'm going to get back
the original shapes.
So I'm going to get back the
original hidden dimension.
So the question is these parts
are duplicated across GPUs
and it's annoying, as we said,
to keep them synchronized.
As we said in practice, we need
to always use this layer norm.
And if I had some
other operation,
I also need to make
sure it's replicated.
So can we just
distribute them as well?
And this is what sequence
parallelism tries to solve.
And we're going to use the trick
that we talked about earlier.
So we have an AllReduce.
And we know that AllReduce, its
reduce-scatter and all-gather.
So how can we apply
it in this case?
This is what sequence
parallelism is.
So this AllReduce, I'm
going to replace it
with the reduce-scatter.
And I'm going to--
this identity-- we can
call this an identity.
This identity, I'm going to
transform it to all-gather.
So in the TPU region, I'm
going to shard my activations
along the hidden dimension.
And then I reduce scatter
along the sequence dimension.
So in this sequence
region, SP region,
I have my sequence,
which is sharded by TP.
And then I all-gather it again
to have H, which is sharded.
So basically, I play
between sharding
along the hidden dimension and
along the sequence dimension.
So this is moving
from TP to TP with SP.
And what this helps me
do is multiple things.
So first of all, the
activations that are stored.
So before, I had to store
very big activations here,
which are SBH, but
thanks to sequence
parallelism my size is
always divided by TP.
So this helps me
avoid big activations.
The second thing is it's the
same amount of communications
since AllReduce,
as we've seen, it's
just the reduce-scatter
and all-gather.
So I didn't have to
add any communication.
And the last question
is about layer norm.
So since we did this operation,
should we think layer norms
grids in this case?
And the answer is no.
And for this, let's take
a look at the backward.
So similarly to what we did
before with the matmuls,
you can verify later that the
backward of a reduce scatter
is all gather and the
backward of an all gather
is reduce-scatter.
Basically reduce-scatter
and all-gather,
they are inverse of each other.
So if this is the forward, the
backward becomes like this.
So the backward is I'm
going to do all gather here
and then reduce
scatter here cetera.
So we notice here that
before layer norms
we have reduced scatter.
And thanks to these reduced
scatter that I now added they
take care of synchronizing
the gradients.
So it's really beautiful
that it works out like this.
So thanks to the fact
that now the GPUs,
they don't do the same work,
they see different batches.
And thanks to the fact
that in the backward
I have a reduce
scatter here now,
instead of just assuming
the perfect case
that it's an identity and that
the layer norm would always
stay synchronized.
I just have this all-gather
and reduce-scatter,
and they take care of
synchronizing my gradients.
So you can verify this,
the inverse reduce-scatter
and all-gather later.
And the pros, cons,
so let's take a recap.
So the pros is that now
we're sharding the model
and compute across GPUs.
And we're being memory
and sample efficient
especially sample
efficient, which
is what we didn't have in DP.
And again, we don't
need grad AllReduce
because GPUs are essentially
doing the same work.
And thanks to SP, I don't
need to AllReduce layer norms
as well because they now
have the reduce-scatter
in the backward.
But we still have
the same problem.
We're communication heavy and
the implementation is complex.
And for this
communication heavy,
this is why it's
recommended if you
take a look at the different
distributed training libraries.
They recommend that you use
TP within a single node.
So if you have a
node of 8 GPUs, they
say that it's better
to use TP lower than 8
so that the communications
for TP stay within a node,
so that when you do
forwards and backwards,
you don't get stuck
waiting for the AllReduces
or the reduce-scatter and
all-gather in forwards
and backwards.
So now, we've seen two
axes of parallelism.
And before generalizing
to the others,
let's see what it
means to combine them.
So we've seen the data
parallel, which shards data.
Here, we have data
parallel size three.
And we've seen tensor
parallelism, which shards
the model into dimensions.
So what does it mean
to combine these two?
Well, the cool thing
about the forms of
parallelism that
we've seen that they
are orthogonal of each other.
So if batch is sharded along
the data axis, it's replicated.
So it's replicated here along
the model axis and vice versa.
If the model is sharded
along the TP axis,
it's replicated
along the data axis.
So this helps us make a
mesh of all the parallelism.
Now, we've only seen two,
but later we can see five
or there's even six or seven.
It depends on how many
partners you want.
And in the code, if you look
at TorchTitan or megatron
or narratron, you're
going to see that--
at first, they init
the process group,
so they init all the WORLD_SIZE.
Let's say you have
six GPUs here.
So you're going to create your
TP groups and your DP groups.
And later, you can
just pick on which
axis you want to do the
communication operations.
So for example, I want to
already use along the TP group.
So I'm going to AllReduce
like this and AllReduce
like this along
all the other axes.
So this is the beauty
of this parallelism.
We make sure that they are
orthogonal of each other.
And now, we've gone through
the first two big parallelisms,
the last three I'm going
to go fast over them.
So for PP, it's
much easier than TP.
So we have our layers like this.
And instead of sharding
them horizontally,
I'm going to share
them vertically.
So I'm going to put some
layers on the first GPU,
some layers on the second GPU.
But you can see here that
the problem is for GPU 1,
at the beginning, it doesn't
have any activations.
So it's just going to say
keep waiting for the first GPU
and for the first
GPU after it goes--
after the forward goes
through the first four layers,
it just waits for the other GPU.
So how can we solve this?
And for pipeline
parallelism, there
is what we call PP schedules
pipeline parallelism schedulers.
So the schedulers,
they define how
your GPUs are going to do--
are going to load the data,
and they're going to communicate
activations and gradients
with the other ranks.
So let's start with
a simple assumption.
Each GPU has one
layer of your model.
And we're going to start
with the simplest scheduler,
the all forward, all
backward scheduler.
So we're going to have the
first batch, which is this one.
So it starts at the first GPU.
And then he sends
the activations
to the second GPU and then
third and then fourth.
And then I have another batch.
So the GPUs don't wait.
I'm going to schedule
eight batches.
So all of them, they're
going to do the forwards.
And then they're going
to do the backwards.
So every time one GPU
does the backward,
it sends the gradients to the
previous layer, et cetera.
And I repeat this.
So this is all
forward all backward.
And I schedule multiple batches
to minimize the idle time.
So the idle time is this.
And it's the biggest problem
in pipeline parallelism.
So there is-- the
best way to solve
it is to have more
complex schedulers.
So this is the one forward,
one backward scheduler.
And the name comes from the fact
that if you prioritize backwards
over forwards,
you're going to have
at some point like
in the middle,
you're going to have
a forward, backward.
So they're interleaved
basically, forward,
backward forward, backward.
But we still didn't solve
the pipeline bubble.
This just helps with
the memory a little bit.
So the best way
to solve it would
be to start doing forwards
from this side as well.
And this is what Deepseek
has done in their DualPipe.
So basically, if you
have eight devices,
you're going to distribute the
layers in a round-robin fashion.
So the first layer,
you're going to put it
both on the first
device and last device.
So that both of them, they can
start with data, et cetera.
So there is a forward
that's going like this.
And there's a forward
And then a backward like this,
and then a backward like this.
And you manage the
overlap in the house.
So as we said, it's
easier said than done
because the implementation
is very complex.
And you need to keep
track of the batches
and the forwards
and backwards so
that you send the correct
activations, and this--
and the correct gradients.
So in general,
the pros and cons.
So the pros is that the
communications are cheap.
There is no AllReduce, nothing
to have a headache about.
You just exchange the
activations and the gradients.
And the sharding
is very efficient
because every GPU keeps track
of just a shard of the model.
It's model-agnostic.
I don't care about
the nature's model,
as long as I just have
layers, and I just
send activations and gradients.
And the cons is that I
need to save activations
for multiple micro-batches,
which is annoying.
So for example, if in this case,
I had eight backwards in here,
they scale 20 micro-batches.
So I need to save 20 times the
activations for the different.
So usually for PP and FSDP since
they rely on activations a lot,
we offload the activations.
So we use activation
checkpointing
or now there is
even CPU offloading.
If you have a good GPU, you
can offload the activations
to the CPU, and then
you just load them back
when you need them.
The other annoying thing is, if
you want to hide the PP bubble,
you need an advanced pipeline
scheduler like dual pipe.
And the implementation
is complex.
It's very hard and it's
tough to add to the library.
And 13 is you need multiple
micro-batches to hide PP bubble.
So in a sense, this is
like the deep issue,
is that you need to
scale your global batch
size with the PP size.
And the last two
parallelisms, they
are specific to two use cases.
For example, for CPP, the
issue we want to solve
is sequence parallelism.
So once you scale your sequence
length, the activations,
they explode.
So the question--
even with TP, even
with PP, the question
is, how can we
amortize the memory cost when
doing long contact training?
So what we've seen previously
in data parallelism, when
we have a batch, we can shard
it along the batch dimension.
But the other-- what
we can do now is let's
shard it along the
sequence dimension.
So it's analogous
to data parallelism.
But if I do that, and if I
give a different sequences
to the GPUs, what
about attention?
Because when I do
the forward, each GPU
has only a part of the sequence.
So how can I compute attention
over my entire sequence?
This is where ring
attention comes from.
And the idea is similar
to online softmax that
is used in flash attention.
So you don't need to compute
softmax out of the box.
You can compute it
in an online fashion.
So each GPU, they
compute softmax locally
and then they exchange K
and V with the other GPUs.
Then they update the
softmax, et cetera.
So this is the idea
behind ring attention.
So the problem with
this, the small problem,
is that we need to communicate
K and V inside the attention
block.
So inside each
attention block, which
is a similar problem to TP, so
it's also communication heavy.
And for that, we can use send
receive operation for GPUs
to send the other case.
And this you can also
use all-gather for that.
So the pros is it's
the only parallelism
that efficiently partition
large sequences memory, sorry.
And because the
other parallelisms,
they don't really
shard the sequence.
So if you have a big
sequence, there's a problem.
The cons is that it's
communication heavy
because in each attention
block, you need to exchange
K's and V's.
And similar to DP, since
each GPU sees different data,
we need to AllReduce
the gradients
and it doesn't help much
for short sequences.
So really, it's really
used if and only
if you're doing long
context training.
And for the last one
EP, it's used for MoEs.
And for MoEs, we don't have
time to go really through them.
But how can we parallelize them?
So when you have
your router and you
want to route your tokens
to different experts,
you can just shard your
experts across GPUs.
So the question
would be, what comes
would I add so that
I can do the routing?
For routing, there is a switch
transformer and top K version.
So let's talk about top K,
which is the more generic one.
For this, let's take a look
at all-to-all operation.
So all-to-all, it's
the most generic way
of exchanging messages.
So basically, you
have, for example,
four processes, four GPUs.
Each one of them, they have
four different messages.
So all-to-all what it
does is just each process,
it's going to send their
messages to the other four.
And each process is going to get
messages from the other four.
So in a sense, all
processes, they
communicate with each other.
It's like an n squared
type of communication.
It's the more-- it's
the most complex one.
And how does this apply in MoEs?
So let's say each GPU
has different experts.
So when you're
doing the routing,
each GPU is going to have
some tokens that need
to be routed to the first GPU.
So this is why all-to-all helps.
So the first GPU here,
which has the first expert,
needs to get the
tokens associated
to it from the other GPUs.
So how can we apply
expert parallelism?
First, we shard the
experts across GPUs
and only the experts.
So expert parallelism is
really only applied in MoE.
It doesn't touch attention.
And so to avoid duplicated
work in attention,
we need to share
data across GPUs.
So EP is-- actually, it's not
orthogonal to DP in this sense.
So you also shard data
across expert parallelism.
And we need an all-to-all
communication to route tokens
to their respective experts,
which is the operation
that we call dispatch.
And of course, we also need to
combine them after the experts
to retrieve the
original sequences.
So the problem and the
bigger-- the biggest problem
that you're going to
face when scaling MoEs.
So how do we know what
all-to-all dispatch to use?
So basically, in order to know
how the tokens are routed,
you need for the router
to compute the scores.
So the CPU needs to
wait for the router
to compute the expert scores.
And this is annoying.
Why?
Because the CPU needs
to wait here for the GPU
to do the router
calculation, what we
call the dispatch preprocess.
And the GPU needs to tell us
what are the buffer sizes,
and what are the tokens
per expert that we need.
And to solve this, there's, for
example, deep EP by Deepseek
and there is hybrid
EP by NVIDIA.
And the only way
to solve this is
to use recent hardware so
far, which has IBGDI and RDMA.
So these allow us to--
so they allocate specific
SMs and specific memory
to basically--
whenever they
calculate or they know
which tokens to
route to each GPU,
they have already allocated the
memory for that calculation.
And this is a problem
because for example,
if you have H hundreds or if you
don't have InfiniBand network,
you're stuck with
this CPU-GPU sink.
And this is why most labs
who do MoE trainings,
they have very slow
trainings just because
of this problem of hardware.
And even the Deep EP, that
Deepseek has open source,
you're going to find
out that it only works
on IBGDI, which is InfiniBand.
So the other labs have a hard
time catching up with this.
So in summary,
expert parallelism
is the only way to
distribute MoEs efficiently,
and it's communication heavy.
It needs an all-to-all,
every MoE block.
And since it has
different data, it
needs to all reduce gradients.
And there is a
CPU-GPU sync, which
slows down your
training very much
to launch this batch operation.
So in summary, it is only to be
used for MoE trainings and/or--
so the practical
solution that people
do to train with
expert parallelism
is to combine it with PPE.
And how do they do that?
So we said that the dispatch
and combine are slow.
And if you remember, for our
one forward, one backward,
we can overlap the
forward and the backward.
So what we do here is-- so
we have two batches, which
is the blue and the green here.
So when we want to do
the dispatch, which
is for the blue
batch, in parallel,
we can do the backward
for the other batch.
And this is nice because--
so MLP here doesn't
need this batch.
And we can do the dispatch here.
And once this is done,
we can do the dispatch
for the other batch, et cetera.
And this is already
implemented in some libraries.
For example in Megatron,
you can use these two flags.
So in a nutshell, you can
combine all five parallelisms.
And you're going to have
different communications
in different steps
of your training.
And we've seen that CP and
EP-- so EP only applied to MoEs
and it only touches the MoE.
And CP only touches
self-attention here.
And yeah, all parallelism
are orthogonal.
So you can combine
all five of them.
And yeah, as a recap, we've
seen the five parallelisms.
And you can find a
cheat sheet that we
made in the Ultra-scale
Playbook on how
to make decisions following
the number of GPUs you have.
And finally, if you're more
interested in the infra
side of things, you can take
a look at the small training
playbook in the infra section.
We've made a lot of
benchmarks on how infra can
handle these types of workload.
And you can find more references
in the two books mentioned.
Also, the Jax Scaling Book
for TPU point of view.
And if you're interested
in these kind of things,
contributions are
very welcome, so
Nanotron, Torchtitan,
Megatron-LM,
and a lot of other libraries.
So feel free to reach out
if you want to contribute.
And one last thing is as we
scale to thousands of GPUs,
let's be mindful of their energy
impact and use them responsibly.
Thank you.
OK.
We'll take any questions
in person or over Zoom.
Any in the room?
Yeah, thanks for the talk.
It seems that for
expert parallelism,
you also have to have the tokens
routed evenly across ranks.
Because if all of your tokens
end up routed to one GPU,
then everything else is idle.
What are ways to fix
this in practice?
That's what the load
balancing tries to do.
So depending on which approach,
for example, Deepseek,
they initially introduced
the load balancing loss.
Sorry.
So the load balancing
acts basically
in the loss, a
factor that penalizes
uneven distribution of tokens.
And there's multiple
ways to do it.
There's the auxiliary
loss free where you just
add a bias term when
you compute the router,
and it would automatically
adjust the distribution
so that it's even across GPUs.
We also have some on Slido.
One is, do different parallelism
strategies meaningfully
affect scaling efficiency model
performance or convergence,
or do they just enable
reaching larger scales?
What's the first one,
scaling convergence?
Efficiency.
Convergence efficiency.
I think they would like scaling
laws of language models.
OK.
So actually, the
different policies
do not change the
forwards and backwards.
So ideally, if everything
is implemented correctly,
it should have the same
effect as if you had one GPU.
So like the same
scaling laws applies.
And you shouldn't find any
difference in using PP over EP
from computation point of view.
Another is, how can we reduce
GPU idle time during, say,
RL training when CPU side
checkpointing or environment
data processing becomes
sequential and a bottleneck?
Yeah.
So for that, at
least for text, you
can allocate a lot of
workers beforehand.
So the PyTorch
data loaders, they
allow you to specify the number
of workers that you can use,
and they can
pre-process the data
before the training workload.
So that should at least help
alleviate the pre-processing
so that it's done before you
even go through the training
iterations.
Any more in the room?
Also, someone asked, do
we have an automatic way
to decide the best parallelism?
Yeah, there have been
some papers for that.
I think if you take
a look at Jax book,
they've played with
that and dilated
the TPU decide on what's
the best parallelism.
But it really depends
on your specific.
So model size, how
many data you have,
the global batch size,
and the network you have.
So the biggest factor in what
we've said when you scale,
of course, is the
network bottleneck.
So if you have, for
example, let's say NVLink.
So in GPUs, usually
NVLink is either
four, eight, or for the most
recent one, 32 or even 72.
So it depends on that.
You can even use the more
communication heavy forms
of parallelism or the less
communication heavy ones.
And for example, for GPUs,
since they are in pods of 32,
usually people, they
allow themselves
to use tensor parallelism
over the 32 pods.
So yeah, it really
depends on the hardware
and the global batch size.
All right.
Thanks, guys.
Thanks so much Nouamane for
the amazing insightful talk.
So let's give it a hand
again for our speaker.